All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today’s דף *daf* is קנ״ט *159*,
159, and it is the ultimate דף *daf* in the penultimate פרק
perek *perek*. So we finish the ninth פרק perek *perek* today, God
willing. Okay, so, and we pick up with אלא אי קשיא הא
קשיא ella i kashya ha kashya, *Ela i kasha ha kasha*. So
this is, it's by היה יודע *Haya yodea*, it’s about 20 lines
down in קנ״ט *159*. So it’s where we’re in a very strange
state of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said,
well, they sent this message from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל
*Bavel* and then they said, here’s the הלכה halacha *halakha*, and this
is a hard הלכה *halakha*, קשה שבדיני ממונות Kasha Shebidinei Mamonos. *kasha
she-be-dinei mamonot*. This was like, you know, one of the hardest or
a very hard הלכה *halakha* in דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically analyzed what the reason of the הלכה *halakha*
was and said, so what’s hard about it? It makes total sense.
So that leads the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to now sort of going
on a search for the explanation of or to try to find
out what was actually the הלכה *halakha* that they sent that they
said was קשה שבדיני ממונות *kasha she-be-dinei mamonot*. Okay, but the one
that we last said, and the reason I’m saying this not to
ruin the surprise is that we’re going to get back to it,
is that it spoke about a son here who pre-sold his inheritance.
Reuven, Yaakov’s son, pre-sold his inheritance to Mordechai, and then Reuven died,
and then Chanoch came and reclaimed it. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
said, well, that makes sense because now the reason that seems unfair
is because you would think Chanoch is getting his inheritance through his
father Reuven, thank you very much, and therefore, how can he reclaim
it since it’s going through his father Reuven, the sale should be
good? I mean, we’ve mentioned the obvious problem of how do you
pre-sell an inheritance? תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a different way of learning
it, we’re going to bracket that issue. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
said, well, that’s fine because, you know, a grandson maybe inherits directly
from his grandfather and bypasses his father, so it makes sense that
he should be able to reclaim it without the sale going through
Reuven and without it being good. So why are you saying that
this is קשה שבדיני ממונות *kasha she-be-dinei mamonot*? So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* now attempts a different explanation of what was the ruling that
was sent and why it is קשה שבדיני ממונות *kasha she-be-dinei mamonot*.
So let’s take a look. אלא Ela, *Ela*, says the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, אי קשיא kashya, הא קשיא kashya *i kasha ha kasha*. If
there was a ruling that was difficult, it’s the following ruling that
was sent and this is the one that was difficult. היה יודע
לו עדות בשטר *Haya yodea lo edut bishtar*. So somebody, you know,
Reuven signed on a שטר shtar *shtar* that Charlie here borrowed $1,000
from David. Okay, עד שלא נעשה גזלן Gazlan *ad she-lo naaseh gazlan*.
Now he signed on that שטר shtar *shtar* while he was a
nice upstanding, you know, upstanding man. ונעשה גזלן Gazlan. *ve-naaseh gazlan*. And
then after he signed his name on that שטר shtar. *shtar*,
the שטר shtar *shtar* for David, he, Reuven, went and started a
life of crime. Now, now this שטר shtar *shtar* comes to court.
Okay, now David’s signature is okay because it’s because, you know, it’s
the signing of the שטר shtar *shtar* is like the presenting of
the testimony in בית דין beis din *beis din*. So he presented
his testimony in בית דין beis din *beis din* before he was
a גזלן Gazlan *gazlan*. So even though now he’s a non-valid witness,
when he signed the שטר shtar *shtar* and when it was like
the testimony was given, he was a כשר kosher. עד *kosher ed*.
The only problem is is that the שטר shtar *shtar* comes to
בית דין beis din *beis din* and it’s not מקיים *mekayam*, the
signatures aren’t validated. Okay, and for David to use the שטר shtar
*shtar* against Charlie, he’s got to validate the signatures. Well, the best
person to validate the signatures is the signatory themselves. So you want
to ask Reuven to come and testify that’s his signature. Okay, the
problem is is that he’s not a כשר kosher? עד *kosher ed*,
he can no longer testify that that’s his signature. Okay, so, הוא
אינו מעיד *hu eno meid*. He cannot testify to his own signature.
על כתב ידו *al ktav yado*. אבל אחרים מעידים aval acherim me'idim.
*aval acherim meidim*. Okay, or some have the גרסא *girsah* יכולים לקיים
כתב ידו *yecholim lekayem ktav yado*. Other people can say, yeah, that’s
Reuven’s signature. All right, that makes sense, but so that we understand
that ruling, totally makes sense. Now, but why is this conceptually קשה
שבדיני ממונות *kasha she-be-dinei mamonot*? So here’s why it’s קשה *kasha*. השתא
איהו לא lo, מהימן אחריני מהימני *hashta ihu lo meheman acherim mehemani*?
So he would himself can’t testify to his own signature. Other people
should be able to? Now what’s ironic about that? Because when other
people are testifying to his signature, they’re basically just validating his own
testimony, but his own testimony is inadmissible. So now still you should
say wait, there’s a big difference. His own testimony is inadmissible today.
When people are מקיים *mekayam* his signature, they are testifying to the
fact that he gave testimony a year ago when he was a
כשר kosher עד *kosher ed*. So what’s the big problem? He’s an
inadmissible witness today, but you can testify that he gave testimony a
year ago, which is what these other people are doing. So the
way the רשב"ם *Rashbam* explains why this is difficult is because all
they’re really testifying to, they’re not testifying when they validate his signature
that he gave testimony a year ago, they’re testifying that that’s... signature.
Okay, but maybe what ראובן Reuven, did was just today or yesterday.
He forged the document, he wrote the document and put on last
year's date when he wasn't yet a גזלן Gazlan. and then wrote
his signature. Right? So how do you know, the reason that you
have to validate is because you're afraid that there's something suspicious, forgery,
it's not all on the up and up. All right. Now ראובן,
Reuven's we now know today we know is a גזלן. Gazlan, He's
been a גזלן Gazlan for the last six months. Okay, so
who knows? People can pay him off or he'll do anything for
money, he'll forge the document for money. So our suspicion is that
maybe he forged this whole document and he just signed it yesterday
but predated it a year ago when he was still כשר. kosher
So what the good does it do that other people have validated
his signature? יישר כח, Yasher koach, you told us he signed it.
But when did he sign it? A year ago or a day
ago? If we're suspicious that he's dishonest, maybe he wrote and signed
this document yesterday and predated it from a year ago. And therefore
how does the validating of his signature mean anything? Okay, so that's
not stated in the גמרא Gemara but that's the way the רשב״ם
Rashbam explains why it's a problem. All you've told us is that
he signed it. But we still don't know right now we can't
trust him, so how do we know he didn't sign it today?
How do we know that he signed it a year ago when
he was still כשר? kasher. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומאי
קושיא, Umai Kushya, but why is that difficult? You know, it's so
funny, we want to end on a place where it's difficult to
explain that line קשה שבדיני ממונות. So it says, oh, I can
explain that. ומאי קושיא דילמא הכא נמי כגון שהוחזק כתב ידו בבי
דין. Umai Kushya dilma hacha nami kegon shehuchzak kesav yado bevei din.
Maybe here it was we already knew his signature. Now what does
that mean we already knew his signature? So תוספות Tosafos gives the
explanation. It means no, no, no, no. Here this שטר shtar was
seen by בית דין beis din a year ago. Okay, it's just
we never got around to validating the signatures. But it was seen
by בית דין beis din with ראובן Reuven signature when ראובן Reuven
was not yet a גזלן. Gazlan Okay, maybe that's the case. So
now ראובן Reuven's became a גזלן, gazlan he can't validate the שטר
shtar because his testimony is no longer admissible. Other people can validate
the שטר. shtar But once other people validate it then we know
it was good testimony from before he was a גזלן gazlan because
we saw the שטר shtar a year ago with this signature. We
didn't have proof it was ראובן Reuven signature, it was not validated
then, but we saw it when ראובן Reuven was still a כשר
kasher. witness. So once we get the signature validated we know that
ראובן Reuven gave his testimony when he was still a כשר kosher,
witness. Yes?
It calls into question the whole idea of using signatures and validating
signatures on a שטר shtar because presumably if the idea is that
maybe this now גזלן gazlan?
signed it and forged the date. Right? So presumably this is with
the complicity of the מלווה malveh
or- right?
Well you could say that on any שטר shtar if you don't
have the signatory witnesses in front of you and you validate that
their signatures are the right signatures you don't validate the date.
Right. So the point is that on any normal שטר shtar since
the people whose signatures are there are people that we know to
be upstanding citizens, right? Once you give testimony that it's their- they've
actually signed it and we know that they are כשרים, kesherim, you
know, so then we assume oh, well they signed it, obviously we're
going to assume they did the honest thing. But the problem here
is that even if we know he signed- there's two possibilities. Number
one is maybe the
מלווה malveh or just wrote it himself and forged the signatures. So
that's what the קיום שטר kiyum shtar says, the signatures aren't forged.
Now that we know the signatures aren't forged we know it's actually
like ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon themselves have done it. Okay, so did they do it
properly or not? If they're good guys we assume they did it
properly. If they're גזלנים gazlanim then we're suspicious that's exactly this question.
Yeah.
So there's another interesting thing here which is we assume that there's
actually a time when this person was כשר. kosher
So we're not retroactively- we're not thinking that he was always a
גזלן gazlan. from the time we know. Right, that's true. That is
correct.
That is correct. He's only a גזלן gazlan from the time we
know that he did that he did it.
So that brings the question how does one get declared to have
this halachic status of a גזלן?
gazlan
There's testimony that he acted that way. If it was a rabbinic
sin it would have to be both testimony that he did the
sin and that it was a הכרזה, hachraza, it was publicly announced
that he was פסול. pasul. If it was a biblical sin it
doesn't have to be publicly announced, but there has to be testimony
that he did the act of a certain date and from that
date on he's פסול. pasul. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says so
look you're right, it would be very difficult if we had only
seen the שטר shtar, today. But we're going to say that the
case is that he saw the שטר shtar last year. So
either if it's difficult you're right it doesn't make sense and we
shouldn't פסקן pasken it if we just saw the שטר shtar today.
And the ruling does make sense when we saw the שטר shtar.
a year ago when ראובן Reuven was still כשר. kosher And then
is how we agree with the ruling, but it's not כשר שבדיני
ממונות. kosher shebidinei mamonot. So the
גמרא Gemara says אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא, ella i kashya ha
kashya. fine, here was the thing that was the difficult ruling. היודע
לו עדות בשטר עד שלא תיפול לו
בירושה.
hayode'a lo edut beshtar ad shelo tipol
lo biyerusha. So basically ראובן Reuven, knew that had signed some שטר
shtar, that he was not a party to,
he had no vested interest in. Okay? He was never going to
be an heir. But then what happened was that the person who
was the person who would have won based on the documents, the
person who was the beneficiary of the document, it turned out that
became somebody that he could inherit from. How could that happen? Well,
let's say he married this man's daughter. Okay? And now if this
man gets property and dies and his only child is his daughter,
it'll pass on to his daughter and from his daughter it'll pass
on to ראובן, Reuven right? So ראובן Reuven can no longer testify
to this guy because he stands to benefit from this guy. He's
in the line of inheritance. Alright? So היודע לו עדות בשטר עד
שלא תיפול לו בירושה, hayode'a lo edut beshtar ad shelo tipol lo
biyerusha,
at the time he signed the document he did not stand to
gain from it.
And now he stands to gain. Can he validate his signature? So
it says הוא אינו יכול לקיים כתב ידו ולכן יכולים לקיים כתב
ידו. hu eino yachol lekayem ketav yado velachen yacholim lekayem ketav yado.
Same point. Okay? And the question is, I don't get it, right?
But if we're suspicious that now because he has a vested interest
maybe he forged it, so even if other people validate the signature
from a year ago, maybe he just wrote the signature yesterday. Maybe
he wrote the document yesterday. Same question. Once we think that this
guy is dishonest, it doesn't matter that we validate his signature. Maybe
he wrote it, he dated it a year ago when he was
כשר, but he just wrote it yesterday. So the גמרא Gemara says
the same answer. ומאי קושיא? umai kushya? Why is it difficult? דילמא
הכא נמי כגון שהוחזק כתב ידו בבית דין. dilma hacha nami kegon
shehuchzak ketav yado beveit din. Okay, you're right. I mean if we
hadn't seen the שטר shtar earlier and it just came before us
today, we wouldn't accept the validation because we would say maybe ראובן
Reuven, wrote it today even though he dated it from a year
ago. But the case we will assume is a case when we
saw the שטר shtar earlier. And since we saw the שטר shtar
earlier, so then as long as we can validate that he was
a signature then it'll be good then we'll know that it was
signed when he was still a כשר witness. Okay, so that's same
thing, same answer. אלא Ela, אי קשיא kashya. הא קשיא. kashya. Fine,
it's the following ruling. היודע לו עדות בשטר עד שלא נעשה
חתנו.
hayode'a lo edut beshtar ad shelo
na'asa chotno. Person knew, I would assume similar to the example I
gave before, but this one let's sort of bracket out any question
about ירושה. yerusha. Okay? Somebody or it's here it's not the son-in-law,
it's the father-in-law. Okay, so well, whatever, anyway. So
somebody
knew testimony about Charlie there before he had married Charlie's daughter. And
now ונעשה חתנו, vena'asa chotno,
now he became Charlie's father-in-law, his daughter married, no did I say
it wrong? I said it wrong. I said it wrong. This guy
knew testimony for Charlie before his daughter married Charlie. Now his daughter
married Charlie and he became Charlie's father-in-law. Okay, now he doesn't stand
to inherit from Charlie, okay, there's no monetary benefit, but he is
a קרוב. karov. He's a relative. He became a relative. You could
also say you became a brother-in-law, you became a father-in-law. Okay, but
when he signed the document,
he was not related to Charlie, but now he is.
Because it mentions חתנו. chotno.
Oh, right, חמיו chamiv would be father-in-law, חתנו chotno would be son-in-law.
That's true. Like כלה, kallah, right, that's true. חתנו chotno is son-in-law.
Alright, so I guess my previous example of a son-in-law being in
the line of inheritance wouldn't work. But okay, whatever. Anyway, fine. Either
way, he now became a son-in-law or brother-in-law or whatever he became.
Okay, so ונעשה חתנו. vena'asa chotno. הוא אינו
מעיד על כתב ידו. hu eino me'id al ketav yado.
So now you've got this שטר shtar that was signed when he
wasn't a relative, but now he's a relative. He can't sign on
the שטר, shtar, he can't testify to his signature because he's a
קרוב. karov. He's a relative. אבל אחרים מעידים. So הוא לא מהימן
אחריני מהימני? hu lo meheiman achrinei meheimnei?
He's not believed and others are believed? So now the גמרא Gemara
says וכי תימא הכא נמי כגון שהוחזק כתב ידו בבית דין. vechi
teima hacha nami kegon shehuchzak ketav yado beveit din. Maybe here too
the שטר shtar appeared before בית דין while he, before he became
a relative.
So once we have people validate then we know the testimony was
given in בית דין as it were when he was still a
כשר witness because we saw the שטר shtar. earlier. והאמר רב יוסף
בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן אף על פי שלא הוחזק כתב ידו
בבית דין. veha'amar rav yosef bar minyumi amar rav nachman af al
pi shelo huchzak ketav yado beveit din. No, in this case of
the son-in-law we actually have a tradition that it's talking even if
the שטר. shtar Our only first appears before us today. So now
we have the challenging ruling: here's the שטר, the first time we
saw it was today. This guy can't testify to his own signature
because he's a relative, he has become a relative. Now today he's
a relative. The שטר is dated as of last year. Okay, but
he can't testify cause now he's a relative. Other people can testify.
So the Gemara's question is, but just because other people are testifying,
if he still maybe he still forged it yesterday? How could that
work since we can't believe him today, how can we believe his
signature today? Why should the date in the שטר help us? Maybe
the whole thing was still maybe he himself, you know, he's doing
it because he loves his, he loves his father-in-law, whatever it is,
and therefore maybe that's maybe he's forge- maybe he did the whole
thing yesterday. So the Gemara says, now this next line here is
a line that gets quoted a lot, very important, about understanding who
type- what type of people are פסולי עדות psulei eidus and what
the reason is. So the Gemara says like this: ומה קושיא? U'ma
kushia? Why is it a difficulty? דילמא גזירת המלך הוא. Dilma gzeiras
haMelech hu.
Maybe the reason a relative is invalid is not the reason why
a נוגע בדבר nogea b'davar is invalid. The previous example, the two
people that we suspected of forging the date, of writing the date
last year but having written the שטר today, were a גזלן. gazlan
Okay, why is a גזלן gazlan invalid? Somebody who will do עבירה
aveirah for money, so maybe they will forge documents for money, maybe
they'll give false testimony for money. Why is a נוגע בדבר nogea
b'davar פסול? pasul? Somebody who stands to gain, because we suspect if
you stand to gain from the directly from the testimony, that's gonna
be too big of a temptation and you won't be able to
testify. Why however is a relative invalid? So we would normally be
inclined to think that a relative would be invalid because, you know,
if it's your family, you'll lie for the sake of your family.
Okay, and therefore once it's again a concern of lying, the Gemara's
question is the same: just because he signed, just because we know
it's his signature, but maybe he forged the date. Okay, so now
the Gemara says no, no, no, a relative is not because of
a concern of lying. A relative is גזירת המלך, gzeirat haMelech, is
just an arbitrary ruling, it's a what we'd call a formal exclusion,
and it's a problem, and therefore you cannot testify in a case
if you're a relative even if we have absolutely no concern you
might be lying, okay, as we know sometimes relatives דווקא davka hate
each other rather than like each other, okay? So the Gemara says
the פסול psul of being a relative is not based on a
concern of lying. אלא, says the Gemara, דילמא גזירת המלך הוא, dilma
gzeiras haMelech hu,
דאינהו לא מהימני, d'inhu lo mehemni, that they're not believed, ואחריני מהימני,
v'achrinei mehemni, and people that are non-relatives are believed, ולא משום דמשקרי,
v'lo mishum d'meshakri, it's not because of a concern of lying. דאי
לא תימא הכי, D'ei lo seima hachi, if you don't say that,
משה ואהרן לחותנם, Moshe v'Aharon l'chosnam, why can't Moshe and Aaron be
witnesses for their sons-in-law? Okay, so you know what, we would think
they would lie? You know, no! אלא גזירת המלך. Ela gzeiras Melech.
It's because- sometimes it's interesting, sometimes when some people quote this, like
ראשונים Rishonim quote this to discuss this פסול psul of being a
relative, they don't say- they- they slightly reframe the Gemara: "Why couldn't
Moshe and Aaron
testify for their sons-in-law?" which is the case in the Gemara. They
say: "Why can't Moshe and Aaron come together in בית דין and
testify as- as two witnesses?" So there they're not being relatives to
the interested party, they're relatives to one another. Okay, but that's a
nice example, they're brothers. בחייך! B'chayecha! Of course they would never lie.
So let's just accept the testimony of Moshe and Aaron that come
together to testify about something. אלא מה? Ela mah? You see that
the problem of relatives is a גזירת הכתוב. gzeiras ha'kasuv. Wait a
minute. אלא, so he- אלא גזירת מלך הוא שלא יעידו להם. ela
gzeiras Melech hu she'lo ya'idu lahem. It's a- it's- it's the divine
decree. הכא נמי גזירת מלך הוא שלא יעיד כתב ידו לחותנו. Hacha
nami gzeiras Melech hu she'lo ya'id ksav yado l'chosno. Here too, it's
arbitrary, it's a- just that's the rule, it's a technicality, you can't
testify to your brother- to your son-in-law's signatures, but we don't suspect
you of lying. And now it all makes sense. Now once other
witnesses validated your signature, now we still assume that you're a good
guy, we assume you're a trustworthy guy. Okay, there's only a technical
problem
that your testimony is not admissible because you're a relative. Now that
we know it was a good signature and you're genuinely the one
who signed it, well we assume therefore that the date is truthful,
a normal person right? And therefore since we- because we never suspect
you of lying and since we assume the date is truthful, we
combine that and we see that you gave your testimony before you
were a relative. So the other cases, we would have to have
seen the שטר earlier, because since we suspect you of lying, even
though we know it's your signature, maybe you just wrote it yesterday
and predated it. But a- but a relative, once we know it's
your signature, then we're not gonna suspect a predating, and we're gonna
assume it was dated properly and it was dated from the time
when you weren't a relative, and therefore it's good. Everybody has their
hand up, we'll start in the back and move forward.
First of all, this is the general principle of why קרובים krovim
can't sign like anything, like the two witnesses.
Right, exactly. It comes from the גמרא. Gemara Well, the principal, the
legal principle is learned from פסוקים pesukim and so on. The explanation
is here, which is basically there is no explanation, that's just the
way it is.
Okay, and where was the famous situation that the גמרא Gemara knows
of where אהרן Aharon or משה Moshe might have been a signature
for their son-in-law?
No, it doesn't know of a situation. We're talking about sons-in-law and
we would say let's imagine a court case. משה Moshe wanted to
testify, משה רבנו Moshe Rabbeinu came to court and wanted to testify
for his son-in-law. Would you let him testify? No. What, you don't
trust משה רבנו? Moshe Rabbeinu? Doesn't matter, that's the rule. Okay, yes,
Dov.
So if it's a priority, you could say that some cases of
a גזלן is also a formalism, like someone was under such extreme
pressure or they
committed a crime,
and ordinarily we
would say he's an honest person.
Yeah, I mean, you know, if somebody was ממש mamash אנוס onus
when they were committing a crime, it would be different. But you're
right, like why don't we read a certain act as an exception
rather than as characterological? So that's why the גמרא Gemara sort of
says it. Well, you know, you stop being a גזלן if you've
done תשובה, tshuva, you know. So, meaning, so we sort of are
willing to see it as a one-time thing if there's evidence that
that's not who you are anymore.
So, but you're right. I mean, look, to some degree we're going
to, you know, we're not going to have to do like, you
know, I mean I assume American courts if they want to bring
like what do you call it, like impugn somebody's testimony, you know,
they bring circumstantial evidence and then the court has to decide does
that undermine the trustworthiness, whereas as we know הלכה works more by
rules. At the end of the day, even though it's based on
a concern of lying, there's still going to be some formal rules.
Right, that's correct. So, yeah, let's go back to David's picture. Yeah.
חותנו chotno and
חותנם chotnam are translated by Koren as father-in-law.
Ha! Okay. Thank you for that. All right. Just to prove
last time I thought I was wrong, I was mistaken. Okay, yes.
But there's a problem here.
Yes. משה רבנו's Moshe Rabbeinu not related to his father-in-law.
I know, but משה's Moshe father-in-law was יתרו. Yitro. I was thinking
about the חותן choten and משה, Moshe, you know, משה's Moshe father,
but anyway, yeah. Okay, yeah.
And I guess you can question that using משה Moshe and אהרן
Aharon as examples of relatives. I mean, nobody is questioning their honesty,
but relatives in general might have many reasons why they're...
Right, meaning I agree with you, meaning it might be true and
that sort of echoes Dov's point. Like there are some formalisms, right,
it sort of echoes Dov's point, there are some formalisms. So it
could be that relatives is based on a concern of dishonesty but
we have to have basic rules and therefore we apply it in
all cases. So just as there's some cases where the reason doesn't
exactly match doesn't mean that that's not the reason. Right? That's sort
of implicitly what Dov was asking. The difference still is that in
the cases about a גזלן or a נוגע בדבר, nogaya bdavar, the
reason is always present and you'd have to say oh, this is
a special case that the reason shouldn't be relevant. Whereas in relatives,
they're like it's a very broad פסול psul and not all cases
of relatives are there real concerns of dishonesty, you know. So that's
why the גמרא Gemara sort of feels free of saying that it's
that it's arbitrary. But you're right. There's certainly many cases of relatives
where it's not arbitrary and there is a concern that somebody might
be lying, you know. So...
I always would have thought in the totally opposite direction, like they
say in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, you know, when they first come
in, consider them guilty and then afterwards after it's decided then consider
them like
relatives. I would think there's more of a concern...
Right, but that's why people that are general... Right, you're right, but
then they never get cleared from that concern just because people testify
to a signature, how are they ever clearing this guy from the
concern that he might be doing it out of because he's, you
know, related to this guy, you know. So that... Anyway, so there
definitely is still a חידוש chiddush here. You're right. And the גמרא
Gemara could have still said that. It is still קשיא, kashya because
even though it's true that it's a formalistic פסול, psul, you never
fully free yourself from a cloud of suspicion that you're maybe you're
doing it because you're related to the guy. But the גמרא Gemara
now feels, no, this makes total sense. So we still don't know
what the ruling was that they said was כשר בדיני ממונות. kasher
b'dinei mamonot. אלא אמר רבא לעולם כדאמינא מעיקרא. Ela amar Rava l'olam
k'damina me'ikara. It's like we said here, this was the ruling which
is that, you know, חנוך Chanoch can come and take the property
away that his father pre-sold to מרדכי Mordechai that his father inherits.
And the גמרא Gemara says, well why is that difficult? Maybe חנוך
Chanoch just inherits it straight from יעקב Yaakov and not through ראובן,
Reuven, so he's entitled to the property and it doesn't have to
sort of go through his father. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
if it was קשיא to you, you were bothered: תחת אבותיך יהיו
בניך, Tachat avotecha yihiyu banecha, in the place of your father, of
you're talking to ראובן, Reuven. and your father will be your son
חנוך, Chanoch, so it means that חנוך Chanoch here directly inherits from
יעקב, Yaakov, he takes the place of his grandfather, and that shows
that it could bypass, and since it bypasses he can just say
give me the property, it never went through my father. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, ההוא בברכה כתיב, Hahu b'vracha ktiv, that's not
a legal point, that's just like a
blessing. So means that your grandchildren will sort of bring good name
to their grandparents and so
on and extend the reputation, but it does not mean that it's
a legal principle that you inherit straight from your grandfather. You inherit
through your father and if you're inheriting through your father, then that
sale should have been valid. So the גמרא Gemara says, and that's
why it's קשיא בדיני ממונות, kashya bedinei mamonus, okay? It's still the
ruling, but there's a conceptual problem here since you're getting it through
your father. So now the גמרא Gemara says, וממאי דההוא בברכה כתיב?
umimmay dehahu bevracha ksiv? How do you say it's just a blessing?
אבל לענין דינא לא, aval le'inyan dina lo, but it's not a
legal principle that you inherit straight from your
grandfather? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, Baraisa, נפל הבית עליו ועל אביו, nafal habayis alav veal
aviv, עליו ועל מורישו, alav veal morisho, והיתה לו כתובת אשה ובעל
חוב, vehayesa lo kesuvas isha ubaal chov, okay, so remember this case?
Here was the case.
Here's my house, okay,
here's יעקב, Yaakov, okay,
here's his son ראובן. Reuven Now ראובן Reuven
has
no money of his own and he owes money. Okay, here's the
document,
ראובן Reuven, da da da thousand dollars,
million dollars, fine. He owes money to this בעל חוב. baal chov.
Alright, and the question is what order did they die? So the
בעל חוב baal chov wants to say the order they died was
first יעקב, Yaakov, then ראובן, Reuven. okay, and here's חנוך Hanoch down
here that will inherit from ראובן. Reuven
Okay,
so the בעל חוב baal chov wants to say that
first יעקב Yaakov died and then ראובן Reuven and it passed through
him and I got my liens on that property, right? That's what
the בעל חוב baal chov wants to say. Whereas חנוך Hanoch wants
to say, no way, first ראובן Reuven. died, then יעקב, Yaakov, and
I inherited straight from granddad. Okay, you got it? Now of course
this is a case of getting from your grandfather with your father
dead. Are you conceptually getting through your father? Because if in this
case חנוך Hanoch is still conceptually getting through his father even with
his father dead, right, then the בעל חוב's baal chov liens should
still apply. So the fact that he wants to say this claim
is going to save him from it basically seems to say that
you can inherit directly from your grandfather and therefore, exactly like this,
it's not just בברכה. bevracha. The grandson can get directly from the
grandfather. Okay, which again makes this ruling make sense. But we want
this ruling to be
difficult.
Okay. Same word as מבריך mavrich like with כלאים kilayim with the
that go like under—
No, a ברכה, bracha, just the blessing. Yeah, this is just a
פסוק pasuk of a
blessing. Your grandchildren—the grandchild—your children will bring good reputation to your father.
Grandchildren will bring good reputation to their grandparents, okay? It's not about
that they stand in stead of them to directly inherit from them.
Inheritance works through the—through the son. והתניא, vehatanya, wait a minute, נפל
הבית עליו ועל אביו, nafal habayis alav veal aviv, עליו ועל מורישו,
alav veal morisho, והיתה לו כתובת אשה ובעל חוב. vehayesa lo kesuvas
isha ubaal chov. יורשי האב אומרים הבן מת ראשון ואחר כך מת
האב. yorshei haav omrim haben meis rishon veachar kach meis haav. Okay,
so first the son, then the father. ובעל חוב אומר האב מת
ראשון ואחר כך מת הבן. ubaal chov omer haav meis rishon veachar
kach meis haben.
So מי לאו יורשי האב
בני—so mi lav yorshei haav bnei the—those who inherit from the father
are the sons, the son of ראובן. Reuven. Okay, I think it's
the son of ראובן. Reuven,
Yeah, yes exactly, the son of ראובן, Reuven it's חנוך. Hanoch. Okay,
מורישו אחי, morisho achei, and the sons of the—the other case is
not father but the one who is מוריש morish to him and
that would be the brothers. Let me just—let's just bracket that, that's
confusing and it's not really relevant for us. But the point is
in the case of the father,
it's ראובן's Reuven son that is saying, ראובן Reuven died first and
I get straight from granddad. Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך לא מצי אמר
מכח אבוה דאבא קאתינא, veisalka dachach lo matzi amar mikoach avuh deaba
kasina, but if you say that legally a grandson does not directly
inherit from his grandfather, a grandson inherits through his father, so דכי
כתיב בברכה כתיב, dechi ksiv bevracha ksiv,
and that's just a ברכה, bracha, it's not a legal principle that
a grandson gets straight from the grandfather. Okay, כי מת הבן ואחר
כך מת האב מאי הוי? ki meis haben veachar kach meis haav
mai havay? Who cares that ראובן Reuven died first and then
יעקב? Yaakov? נימא להו בעל חוב ירושה דאבוכון קא שקליתו, neima lehu
baal chov yerusha deavuchon ka shaklis, you are getting your father's inheritance
so conceptually even if ראובן Reuven, died first, conceptually it came through
your dead father. And therefore I have rights to it. Okay? So
the fact that the בעל חוב ba'al chov makes that claim shows
that a grandfather's inheritance bypasses the son and goes straight to the
grandson. So that's what the גמרא Gemara, says, seems to be pretty
good proof. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, that's
not necessarily the case. יורשי האב yorshei ha'av are אחיו, achiv, his
brothers, okay? Meaning not חנוך, Chanoch, there's no חנוך Chanoch here. Okay?
What there is is
ראובן, Reuven, there is not only ראובן, Reuven there's also שמעון, Shimon,
right? ראובן's Reuven brother.
And he's outside the house.
He's outside the house, he was smart. Okay, he stayed outside the
house. So here's the possibilities.
If יעקב Yaakov died first, if ראובן Reuven died first, then there
is then יעקב Yaakov dies, it goes to יעקב's Yaakov remaining son.
It goes like this. יעקב's Yaakov remaining son. Okay? If יעקב Yaakov
died first, so what happens if יעקב Yaakov died first? If יעקב
Yaakov died first, half goes to ראובן Reuven and half goes to
יעקב, Yaakov, okay to שמעון, Shimon, sorry. Half goes to ראובן Reuven
and half goes to שמעון. Shimon. And then and then you know
and then ראובן Reuven dies and then after here so let's just
do it like this okay so so this is if if יעקב
Yaakov died first then wait did I get it right? I'm sorry
hold on sorry.
If ראובן Reuven died first the blue is one scenario ראובן Reuven
died first then יעקב Yaakov then goes then the whole thing goes
to שמעון Shimon he's the only son. Okay. If however okay יעקב
Yaakov died first okay then half of it goes to ראובן Reuven
okay half of it goes right? So יעקב Yaakov died first half
goes to ראובן Reuven half goes to him and then ראובן Reuven
dies so then the half what's going to happen to the half?
Well fine it'll go to שמעון Shimon in the end anyway. But
it went to שמעון Shimon through ראובן Reuven so therefore the creditors
here they get their claw right get their שעבודים shibudim on it
before it passes. In the end שמעון's Shimon going to get it.
But does שמעון Shimon get it all straight from his father? Or
does he get half through his brother and then the creditors got
their hands on it? Okay?
So in either scenario according to that the creditor's going to be
able to collect.
No the creditor only collects if the only creditor only connects if
יעקב Yaakov died first. יעקב Yaakov died first then it goes to
ראובן Reuven. and then it came through ראובן. Reuven But if ראובן
Reuven died first it all went straight to שמעון. Shimon. Okay? So
the point though in this case is is that there's no proof
about grandfather grandson bypassing the son okay because we're not dealing with
grandkids here. Yes it bypasses ראובן Reuven because there's only one remaining
brother in that scenario.
ראובן Reuven dies first it goes to his father?
If ראובן Reuven died first ראובן Reuven doesn't have any property it's
all about יעקב's Yaakov property.
I mean whatever it'd be a different conversation.
He has a debt.
Okay? So if ראובן Reuven dies first שמעון Shimon doesn't inherit his
father's estate through his dead brother. He's the only surviving brother and
he gets the whole estate so there's no proof to our case.
Wait let's just read it. Okay? So it says לא, no, יורשי
האב yorshei ha'av are אחיו achiv his brothers.
מרישא דאבויה merisha de-avuyah I'm not going to deal with מרישא merisha
because it's complicated and it's not relevant for us. So at the
end of the day what the גמרא Gemara, said is this is
the end of the סוגיא. sugya. The גמרא Gemara said in a
case of a grandson which by the way makes sense this is
what we assume. We assume a grandson inherits through his father not
directly. Correct? Everything we learned in the beginning of the פרק about
lines of inheritance. And the proof is by the way which the
גמרא Gemara never really fully answered is that חנוך Chanoch also gets
ראובן's Reuven חלק בכורה. chelek bechorah. So clearly he's representing his father.
So now we finally have the קשיא שבדיני ממונות. kashya she-bedinei mamonot.
חנוך Chanoch is inheriting in place of his father and he is
still voiding his father's pre-sale of the ירושה yerusha to מרדכי. Mordechai.
Okay? So that's the קשיא. The thing that entitles him to get
the property is that he's inheriting through his father. And at the
same time even though it's coming through his father the sale to
מרדכי Mordechai does not is not valid.
How is he going to avoid that?
So the גמרא Gemara then never explains so then if that's true
why is the sale invalid? Right? Part of the problem is is
because how do you pre-sell something? So maybe the only if you
pre-sold it it was more like a promise that ראובן Reuven would
pass it on to מרדכי Mordechai or something right so partly I
think the reason he can void it is because we don't really
understand the mechanics of how ראובן Reuven could pre-sell it in the
first place okay but that's the קשיא. That's why I think it's
קשיא it never really fully explains what the explanation is but presumably
the explanation has something to do... to the fact that it wasn't
really an actual sale. So maybe it was like a right to
collect from me, but it has something to do with it being
ראובן Reuven personally receiving it and being alive. So when it's חנוך
Chanokh is getting it in ראובן's Reuven stead, the sale does not
remain valid. Yes, Rabbi Dov?
Just if ראובן Reuven inherits from his father, all
the land that he inherits from his father will ultimately be the
ירושה yerusha that his son will get when ראובן Reuven himself dies.
Correct.
Absolutely.
Okay, sure. But the question still is if ראובן Reuven, is dead
and then his grandfather dies here, are you conceptually inheriting straight from
your grandfather?
Right, okay, yeah. So since we're not using this verse in תהלים
Tehillim for a halakhic justification...
That is correct.
Now, three verses before that is the famous line כל כבודה בת
מלך פנימה.
Kol Kevuda Bat
Melekh Penima. There you go. Okay. So anyway, now, because here we're
dealing with the idea of inheriting as it were directly or through
a dead parent, okay, we're going to talk a little bit about
this question of, we're going to wrap up with some ירושה yerusha
questions about inheriting through somebody who's already in the grave. Because essentially
in this case what we've now said essentially is, right, חנוך Chanokh
inherits through his father who's in the grave, which happens a lot
in the beginning of בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, that you inherit from
somebody is dead or whatever, and the grandson and the grandson or
whatever, they're sort of inheriting because you view them in the place
of their dead parent.
But now the גמרא's Gemara going to have an important exception to
this rule. Let's take a look. So, בעי מיניה מרב ששת. baei
minei meiRav Sheshet.
Asked רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. בן מהו שיירש את אמו בקבר ולהנחיל
לאחין מן האב. Ben mahu sheyirash et imo bakever vehanchil le'achim min
ha'av. Can a son inherit from his mother who is in the
grave in order to pass on that inheritance to his paternal brothers?
Okay, so that's clear. So let's keep on going.
Now,
what that means is the following.
Okay. So, okay.
Here is יעקב Yaakov and here is רחל Rachel
and you've got יוסף. Yosef. And now you've got him with
לאה Leah and
you've got
ראובן, Reuven שמעון, Shimon, etc.
Their half-brother. Half-brother.
Okay. Now רחל Rachel died בדרך בעוד כברת ארץ לבוא אפרתה. baderekh
be'od kivrat eretz lavo Ephrata. Okay, so
now exactly. Now
here her dad, לבן, Lavan,
okay, now after רחל Rachel died, לבן Lavan dies. All right. So
who
is
going to get לבן's Lavan property? Does לבן's Lavan property go and
now לבן Lavan has some brothers, right? What does it say? He
took his brothers, right? את אחיו עמו וירדוף אחריו. et echav imo
vayirdof acharav. Anyway, fine. Okay.
So there's his brothers. So when לבן Lavan dies, is the property
going to go
to... should we say he has no surviving kids? And because he
has no surviving kids, the property's going to go to his brothers?
Or do we say but he's got a surviving grandkid, right? And
he's got a surviving grandkid. So if he's got a surviving grandkid
maybe it goes to יוסף. Yosef. Okay. But what's going to happen
if it goes to יוסף? Yosef? If it goes to יוסף, Yosef,
then after יוסף Yosef dies, who's going to get that property? Right,
assuming he doesn't have any sons. Then it would continue on to
his brothers, to his half-brothers, and it basically would leave,
it would sort of take it away from לבן's Lavan children. Right,
so if לבן Lavan died first and then רחל Rachel and then
רחל Rachel passed it on to יוסף, Yosef, fine, that would happen,
okay. But there seems to be something that's like a little unfair
here that it's passing not to his child, but to his grandchild...
that's sort of why we're discussing this, right? It's passing like to
his grandchild, but to his grandchild who
is clearly part of a different
family because families are basically patriarchy, right?
Well, it's really a son of a daughter
though in this case, right? Oh, okay, fine, we're not... we won't
make it לאה, Leah, we'll make it דבורה. Devorah. Okay, whatever. Okay,
fine. We're not being that explicit, okay? So the conceptual family here,
right, because we're a patriarchy, remember, like that's the family. Okay. So
if he dies and it goes straight to רחל Rachel even though
רחל's Rachel married to a man from a different family, it's going
to a child, okay.
But if his daughter is dead, right, is it going to go
to somebody who is essentially
part of a different family, which means that it's going to be
going like away from him? Okay, so that's the question.
That you sort of, yeah,
it's going through רחל Rachel בקבר. bakever.
Right, exactly. Now we just got through saying anything unfair to לבן.
Lavan. Exactly. Okay. Now we now again, we just got through saying
that a person basically, you know, is in the stead of their
dead parent. So should be inheriting, right? Normally you would say a
grandchild inherits. Okay, but here there is something that seems like, wait.
Now the question, you know, that would lead to,
you know, anyway, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: בעי מיניה רב ששת: Ba'ei minei Rav Sheshet: בן מהו שיירש
את אמו בקבר
להנחיל לאחיו מן האב?
Ben mahu sheyirash et
imo bakever lehanchil le'achiv min ha'av? Okay, so
now
oh, I think I misexplained it in the following way. If there
was this case, right, I'm sorry, I apologize. If it was this
case, if יוסף Yosef were still alive, it definitely would work. Okay,
I'm sorry, because, you know, what happens in the future is just
a future consequence, that's not our concern. If יוסף Yosef is still
alive, it goes to the grandchild. Okay, so I misexplained that. That's
clear, because, you know, at this moment it's his grandkid, it's his
grandson, so his grandson gets it. Whatever happens happens. The question is
that יוסף Yosef is already dead. Okay, so יוסף Yosef is dead.
Wait a minute, let me just make sure.
יוסף בן רחל שמת בחיי אמו, Yosef ben Rachel shemet bechayei imo,
ואחר כך מתה רחל. ve'achar kach meta Rachel. Ah, okay.
So here's the case. If יוסף Yosef were alive, it would go
to יוסף. Yosef. If רחל Rachel were alive, it would go to
רחל. Rachel. But what happens is that first יוסף Yosef died,
that happened number one, okay, then רחל Rachel died, that's number two,
okay, and now the question is, okay, now that רחל Rachel died...
oh, I'm very sorry.
I'm very sorry, I overcomplicated it, okay? I don't know why I
did that because I was highly influenced by that case. Forget לבן,
Lavan, I take it all back, I overcomplicated it. Okay, there's no
לבן. Lavan. All right? I was getting confused who was in the
קבר. kever. His mother wasn't in the קבר, kever, he was in
the קבר. kever. I apologize, all right, retract all things, I apologize.
Fine, here's what happened. Clouded in there. I'm sorry, okay, I got
confused because of the previous case. Fine, here's the case. יוסף Yosef
dies and then רחל Rachel dies. Well, there's still לבן Lavan in
the following way, which is, I needed to have לבן Lavan here.
I can't... okay, which is, what happens to רחל's Rachel's property? Okay,
do we say, but now you see much more obviously why this
is a problem. Do we say that
רחל Rachel dies and it's like יוסף Yosef inherits him in the
grave and passes it on to his brothers? Okay, so the brothers
are representing their dead brother, as opposed to a son representing his
dead father, his אחיו מן האב. achiv min ha'av. Okay, as opposed
to a son representing his dead father, which is what we had
here, these brothers are representing their dead brother and are going to
get from somebody who is completely not related to them, right? רחל
Rachel is completely not related to ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Or
so you can understand why, no, like
a יוסף's Yosef's son who is רחל's Rachel's grandson, that represents יוסף
Yosef and can inherit. Okay, but ראובן Reuven and but they can't
represent יוסף Yosef and
inherit from the mother. So instead the property would go back to
לבן. Lavan. Okay, all right, so sorry I complicated that, but that's
the question. Can he be יוסף? Yosef? He's בקבר, bakever, not his
mother's in קבר. kever. Can he be יורש את אמו yoresh et
imo when he's already in the grave to pass it on to
his paternal brothers? Okay, so let's read that. Oh my gosh, now
we really have to truck. Okay,
so where were we? בעי מיניה רב ששת: Ba'ei minei Rav Sheshet:
בן מהו שיירש את אמו בקבר להנחיל לאחיו מן האב? Ben mahu
sheyirash et imo bakever lehanchil le'achiv min ha'av? אמר ליה רב ששת
תניתוה. Amar leh Rav Sheshet: Tanituha. We learned it: האב שנשבה ומת
בנו במדינה. Ha'av shenishba umet beno bamedinah. So a father is taken
captive and his son who's left back in the country and is
nice and safe also dies and they both die but in different
geographic locations and you don't know which one died first. It's a
variation of the house falling, okay? You don't know which one died
first. ובן שנשבה ומת אביו במדינה, Uven shenishba umes aviv bamedinah, same
story. יורשי האב ויורשי הבן יחלוקו. Yorshei ha'av veyorshei haben yachaloku. They
split the property. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא דאיכא
תנא, Ileima de'ika tna, היינו יורשי האב והיינו יורשי הבן. hainu yorshei
ha'av vehainu yorshei haben. So
I don't get it, says the גמרא, okay? If that, you don't
know who died first and it's a father and a son, who's
debating it? If you're the father and here's the son, okay, so
who are the other possible יורשי הבן? yorshei haben? Well, it could
be his son or it could be brothers, okay? So does it
matter according to them who's going to get the property, who died
first? No.
If ראובן died first, then he takes the stead. And he gets
from the father. If the father died first, then it gets distributed,
then his father died and he gets from his father, right? So
it doesn't really matter who died first. Everybody's going to get their
fair share because it's all a direct ירושה yerusha case, right? We
never had an okay fine. So that's the גמרא's question. That can't
be the case of the ברייתא braita because then they're all going
to get equally whoever died first.
So היינו יורשי אב והיינו יורשי בן? hainu yorshei av vehainu yorshei
ben? Who are the יורשי אב yorshei av and who are the
יורשי בן yorshei ben that are fighting? They're all the same people.
אלא הכי קאמר. ella hachi kaamar. So it must be we radically
re-read
it. אב שנשבה ומת בן בתו במדינה ובן בתו שנשבה ומת אבי
אביו במדינה. av shenishba umet ben bito bmdinah uven bito shenishba umet
avi aviv bmdinah. No, no, no. The question is not
who died first between the father and the son. The question is
who died first between יעקב Yaakov
and I don't know this is דינה, Dina, okay? And I don't
know who this is. This is דינה Dina whatever,
Davina, I don't know. Anyway, I don't know, anyway, whatever, it doesn't
matter. Anyway, the question here is who died first between the father
and the grandson. Okay? And now why should that matter? What's the
fight? Here's the site. So the fight is like this. ולא ידינן
היי מינייהו מית ברישא. vlo yadinan hai minaihu met brisha. יורשי האב
ויורשי הבן יחלוקו. yorshei haav veyorshei haben yachloku. Okay, now, so they're
going to divide. So the יורשי הבן, yorshei haben, so the יורשי
ה- yorshei ha- whatever,
you know, יורשי האב ויורשי הבן
יחלוקו.
yorshei haav veyorshei
haben yachloku. Okay, so the question is like this, so who would
be let's, so who would be his יורש? yoresh? Well, let's take
a look. ואי איתא היינו נמי דבן מית ברישא
לירת לאבוה דאימיה בקבר
ולהנחילו לאחיו מן אבוה. veim ita hinu nami deben met brisha lirat
lavue deimei bakever ulehanichlo leachiv min avue. So יורשי האב ויורשי
הבן. yorshei haav veyorshei haben. So he's the יורשי האב. yorshei haav
Wait,
wait, wait, he no, no, no, this can't be the יורשי האב
yorshei haav. because then דינה Dina wouldn't get it anyway. It has
to be the יורשי האב yorshei haav are like father's brothers.
Right? Okay.
And the יורשי הבן, yorshei haben,
let's make that his brothers.
So one minute, let me check I got this. יורשי האב yorshei
haav ויורשי הבן. veyorshei haben.
יורשי, yorshei,
wait a minute,
you want to see a chart?
No. I want to first read the לשון. lashon. ולא אם אין
לו בנים vlo im ein lo banim so יורשי הבן קרובי אביו.
yorshei haben krovei aviv. ויורשי
הבן הן קרובי אביו. veyorshei
haben hen
krovei aviv. ויורשי
הבן הן קרובי או
קרובי,
veyorshei haben hen
krovei
o
krovei,
yeah, let me see that chart. I had this figured out last
night.
Oh my god, that's even more confusing. Give me one second, I
had this figured out last night. Okay. ומת בן בתו במדינה. umet
ben bito bmdinah. ויורשי, veyorshei, ומת בן
בתו במדינה,
umet ben
bito bmdinah, ויורשי הבן בן
בתו. veyorshei haben ben bito.
Ah, okay, got it. Okay. The יורשי הבן yorshei haben are, here's
the key. The יורשי הבן yorshei haben are
his are here his, ah, the יורשי הבן yorshei haben are his
half brothers, okay? So these are these, right, these are the יורשי
הבן. yorshei haben.
Exactly this case, קרוביו מן האב, krovav min haav, right, just like
we had before. Okay? That's the יורשי הבן. yorshei haben. Okay? So
everybody got that? Okay? So the half brothers on the father's side.
So they say, they're saying and this is יורשי האב, yorshei haav,
a father's brother because anyway this was his only child, okay? So
these guys say, you know, יעקב Yaakov died first, okay, then דינה
Dina died, then if it's יעקב Yaakov died first, she I think
she's already dead. She starts off being dead. She starts off being
dead. She starts off being dead. It was between this and this,
which one died first. So they say יעקב Yaakov died first, his
grandson inherited, then his grandson died and then we inherited from our
half brother. That's what they say. And this guy says, no, the
grandson died first. He had no living relatives like direct descendants, so
we got it. Okay, that's what they're saying. אה ah says the
גמרא, but this is exactly our case. Why don't we say that
in this case the grandson inherits בקבר? bakever?
Even if even if he died first, let him be יורש בקבר
yoresh bakever להנחיל לאחיו מן האב. lehanichil leachiv min haav. So you
see that when he is dead, it does not go through him
to the paternal brothers, when he is dead, it goes the other
way.
Why don't we go to his father first
instead of the grandson?
His father's dead. Oh.
Okay. Fine. So now the גמרא says like
this: ואם איתא, V'im issa, even if he died first, ניהוי נמי
דבן מת ברישא לירות לאבוה דאימיה בקבר, nihei nami d'ben meis breisha
liyras l'avuha d'imei bakever, right? Let him inherit from his grandfather even
while he is in his grave, as it were, וליורשינהו לאחוה מן
אבא uliyorshinhu l'achava min abba and pass on to his paternal brothers.
So it must be that once this guy is dead, okay, it
does not pass through him through the grave. Okay. Children, right, replace
their father, but not half-brothers. Okay, so it does not pass through
him through the grave. Okay.
How do you read that line again? ואם איתא? V'im issa?
ואם איתא, V'im issa, if it's true that you can inherit through
the grave,
so ניהוי נמי דבן מת ברישא לירות לאימיה בקבר, nihei nami d'ben
meis breisha liyras l'imei bakever, let him inherit from his mother even
after he's dead, even after he is in the grave, וליורשינהו לאחוה
מן אבא uliyorshinhu l'achava min abba and pass on to his half-brothers.
אלא שמע מינה אין הבן יורש אמו בקבר להנחיל לאחין מן האב,
Ella shma mina ein haben yoresh imo bakever lehanchil la'achin min ha'av,
so that's a good proof. אמר ליה רב אחא בר מניומי לאביי.
Amar lei Rav Acha bar Minyumi l'Abaye. So now there's a much
easier proof. אף אנן נמי תנינא. Af anan nami tanina. תוספות says:
why did they need? This is so obvious, they should have started
with this. אף, Af, נפלה הבית עליו ועל אמו. nafla habayis alav
v'al imo. Okay, the case about him and his mother, right? Remember
that case? The house that collapsed on him and his mother?
There, the schools disagree, right?
And the גמרא says אלו ואלו מודים שיחלוקו. eilu v'eilu modim sheyachloku.
They all agree that you divide it. Okay, okay, because basically his
kids wanted to say whatever, well, okay,
ואם איתא, v'im issa, so now why does... so it would be
I guess a similar case, that he has here half-brothers from a
different mother. Okay, there's a different mother, same father. Anyway, he's got
these half-brothers. Okay, so these half-brothers are saying mother died first, then
the son, then we got it from our brother.
And the mother's relatives are saying no, the son died first, and
then I'm going to get, you know, לבן Lavan here's going to
get it back from his daughter, okay? So the גמרא says one
minute, if it's true that you can inherit in the grave, even
if the son died first, it shouldn't go to the mother's relatives,
it should go through her dead son to the half-brothers. It's exactly
this case. Okay? It says who died first, the mother or the
son? And that's the question. So the answer, does לבן Lavan get
it or do the half-brothers get it? So the גמרא is saying
why does it matter? Even if the son died first, if it
could pass through the grave, it's exactly this case. Okay? So the
גמרא says ואם איתא ניהוי נמי דבן מת ברישא לירות לאימיה בקבר.
V'im issa nihei nami d'ben meis breisha liyras l'imei bakever. So the
house here fell on these two people, that was the house. Okay,
but so what? So let him die first, then still as he
dies it should pass on to לבן. Lavan. If this is true,
it should pass through him into the grave to his brothers. וליורשינהו
לאחוה מן אבוה. uliyorshinhu l'achva min avuha. אלא שמע מינה, Ella shma
mina, we see from this, אין הבן יורש אמו בקבר להנחיל לאחין
מן האב, ein haben yoresh imo bakever lehanchil la'achin min ha'av, שמע
מינה. shma mina. The half-brothers do not represent him when he's dead
in order to inherit it from a woman to whom they are
not related to at all. Okay, it's one thing to represent a
relative who's dead if you're related to the person who's passing on
the property, but they cannot represent their dead brother. Or another way
of saying it is he doesn't inherit through the grave and pass
on. שמע מינה. shma mina. Okay.
טעמא מאי? Ta'ama mai? Why? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, נאמרה סיבה בבן
ונאמרה סיבה בבעל. ne'emra sibah b'ven v'ne'emra sibah b'va'al. Right? It says
ולא תסוב נחלה ממטה למטה אחר. v'lo sisov nachalah mimateh l'mateh acher.
And the way that a נחלה nachalah transfers
is a woman inherits and passes on to a son from a
different tribe or passes on to a husband from a different tribe.
Those are the two ways in which that נחלה nachalah can get
diverted, right, when a woman inherits. So מה סיבה האמורה בבעל אין
הבעל יורש אשתו בקבר. ma sibah ha'amura b'va'al ein haba'al yoresh ishto
bakever. The same way by case of husband and wife,
if the woman is dead and then לבן Lavan here dies, לבן
Lavan does not pass it on to his son-in-law once his daughter
is dead. Through the... right? Meaning even though a son inherits from
his wife, if she died first and then the father-in-law dies, the
son-in-law does not get it for obvious reasons. The relationship is severed
once she's dead. Right? It's the... so therefore the same way he
doesn't inherit from his father-in-law once his wife is
dead, okay, so מה סיבה האמורה בבעל אין הבעל יורש אשתו בקבר
אף סיבה האמורה בבן אין הבן יורש אמו בקבר להנחיל לאחין מן
האב. ma sibah ha'amura b'va'al ein haba'al yoresh ishto bakever af sibah
ha'amura b'ven ein haben yoresh imo bakever lehanchil la'achin min ha'av. So
similarly he doesn't inherit when he's dead to pass on to people
he's not related to. And it's the same idea. This would go
to somebody to whom there would be directly to somebody to whom
there would be no relationship, a son-in-law. It's one thing to go
to the daughter and from the daughter to the
son, it doesn't go directly to somebody to whom there's no relationship.
Okay, from the dead mother to those.
So in general you don't inherit the grave.
Right. Okay, let's just give ourselves three more minutes because this the
rest of this is straight quotes from cases we've seen before and
you obviously remember everything you've seen before, so it'll go very quickly.
ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu d'amar lei l'chaverei, somebody said to his
friend, נכסי דבר סיסן מזבנינא לך, Nichsei deBar Sisan mezavinna lach, I'm
going to sell you all of the property of Bar Sisan that
I took possession of. Okay, he presumably he brought from Bar Sisan.
הוי חד ארעא דהוה מקריא דבי בר סיסן, Havi chad ar'a d'hava
mikraya d'bei Bar Sisan, there he had some property that was called
of the house of Bar Sisan, but it was not really purchased
from Bar Sisan. Okay, so is this included in this phrase or
not?
Yes. אמר ליה הלאו דבי
בר סיסן היא וקרויה דמיקריא דבי בר סיסן. Amar lei halav d'bei
Bar Sisan hi u'kruyah d'mikraya d'bei Bar Sisan. So he tried to
say no, that wasn't part of the sale. It's called that, but
it's not genuinely his. אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן, Ata lekamei d'Rav Nachman,
so it came to Rav Nachman, ואוקמה בידא דלוקח, V'ukmah b'yada d'loke'ach,
and Rav Nachman said no, it's called Bar Sisan, it goes to
the buyer. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman,
Rava said to Rav Nachman, דינא הכי, Dina hachi, that's the ruling?
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, he should have to
prove it, the buyer has to prove it, he's coming to take
it away out of the seller's possession. Now, so רמי דרבא אדרבא
ודרב נחמן אדרב נחמן. rami d'Rava a'Rava u'd'Rav Nachman a'Rav Nachman. Now
there's another case where they seem to flip their positions. ההוא דאמר
ליה לחבריה, Hahu d'amar lei l'chaverei, somebody said to his friend, מאי
בעית בהאי ביתא, Mai ba'it b'hai beita, what are you doing in
my house? אמר ליה מינך זבינתה ואכלתי שני חזקה, Amar lei minach
zavinta ve'achalti sheinei chazakah, I bought it from you and I've been
eating for three years, and it's a חזקה. chazakah. אמר ליה אנא
בשכוני גוואי הואי, Amar lei ana b'shikunei gava'ei havai, I was living
in the inner chamber of the house, so
and therefore I was constantly present, and since I was constantly present,
your חזקה chazakah doesn't mean anything. So,
okay, but because it was the inner house, not too many people
saw it. So אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן, Ata lekamei d'Rav Nachman, אמר
ליה זיל ברור אכילתך. Amar lei zil berur achiltach. So Rav Nachman
said, go prove that your eating, meaning your living in the house,
was done and the other guy without the other guy being around.
So put the burden of proof on the person with the חזקה.
chazakah. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman, Rava
said to Rav Nachman, דינא הכי, Dina hachi, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה,
Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, the one, the מוציא motzi has to bring
the proof. Now the מוציא motzi here for Rava is interesting. Once
this guy showed that prima facie he had three years of חזקה,
chazakah, that makes him the מוחזק. muchzak. So the original owner now
becomes the המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero. That was a very interesting idea
when we did חזקה, chazakah, who's the מוחזק. muchzak. So קשיא דרבא
אדרבא ודרב נחמן אדרב נחמן. kashya d'Rava a'Rava u'd'Rav Nachman a'Rav Nachman.
Now although he uses the same phrase המוציא מחברו, hamotzi mechavero, the
Gemara says on the face of it it's a problem because in
one case Rav Nachman is basically awarding it to the buyer in
the case of דבי בר סיסן, d'bei Bar Sisan, but in the
other case of the house, he's defaulting it to the original owner.
And Rava flips it. Do you default it to the original owner
or do you default it to the person with the current claim?
So the Gemara says like this. דרבא אדרבא
לא קשיא,
D'Rava a'Rava
lo kashya, that's not difficult. הכא מוכר קאי בנכסי התם לוקח
קאי בנכסי. Hacha mocher ka'i b'nichsei hatam loke'ach ka'i b'nichsei.
That's the interesting answer. Don't tell me buyer or seller, tell me
who's the מוחזק. muchzak. When I'm selling you the property of דבי
בר סיסן, d'bei Bar Sisan, I'm the מוחזק. muchzak. I have full
possession of this property, the question is was it included in the
sale or not? But I'm the מוחזק. muchzak. When I've been, on
the other case, when the buyer has been shown to three years
of חזקה, chazakah, at least prima facie it's good חזקה, chazakah, he
becomes the מוחזק. muchzak. And the original owner is trying to take
it away from him. That's a very straightforward explanation.
דקאי בנכסי מהני מוחזק. D'ka'i b'nichsei mahani muchzak. Yes. ודרב נחמן אדרב
נחמן לא קשיא. U'd'Rav Nachman a'Rav Nachman lo kashya.
Now why is that not difficult? הכא כיון דאמר ליה דבי בר
סיסן. Hacha kivan d'amar lei d'bei Bar Sisan. Now why does, so
if it's true in both cases Rav Nachman is awarding it to
the non-מוחזק, muchzak, so what's the logic of that? So in the
case of דבי בר סיסן, d'bei Bar Sisan, there's a good logic.
הכא כיון דאמר ליה דבי בר סיסן, Hacha kivan d'amar lei d'bei
Bar Sisan, he said he was selling him דבי בר סיסן, d'bei
Bar Sisan, ומיקריא דבי בר סיסן, u'mikraya d'bei Bar Sisan,
and that's what it's called, so עליה דידיה רמיא מילתא למימר דלאו
דבי בר סיסן היא. aleih dideih ramya milta l'meimar d'lav d'bei Bar
Sisan hi. The other guy has to prove that that's not included
in the term. Right? So he's basically saying it's like, look, that's
the term that was referred to, that's the term that was trade,
you say oh, it's called that but it's not technically what it
is. Prove that that's not meant by the term in the contract.
Okay? So the contract, basically there it's, you know, the other guy's
a מוחזק muchzak but your context supports you. הכא נהי Hacha nehi
about this case about that I have to prove that my חזקה
chazakah was without the other guy being present. Okay, why should that
be true? So he says, לא יהא אלא דנקיט שטרא, Lo yehei
ela d'nakit shtar, because a חזקה chazakah is in the place of
a שטר מכר shtar mecher that shows that I bought it. So
he says even if you have a שטר, sometimes if the שטר
is challenged, you have to prove that it's a valid שטר. So
מי לא אמינא לך קיום שטרות בדקומי נכסי? Mi lo amina lach
kiyum shtarot b'dukmei nichsei? So even if I had a שטר that
said I bought it, if I said that's a forgery, you'd have
to validate the signatures. So you come with your years of חזקה
chazakah and I'm saying that doesn't, that isn't what it looks like.
Now the same way a forgery is just סתם stam speculation, how
dare you say it's a forgery, I've got witnesses signed. Nevertheless, when
that's challenged... You have to be defended against. So when I say
I was living in the inner house, even though I have no
exact proof, I've raised a challenge, you have to do what you
can to prove against it. Okay, how do you prove the absence
of something is not clear, but you know, at least you have
to do something to try to demonstrate that that was false. Okay,
הדרן עלך מי שהוציאו, Hadran alach mi shehotziu, שקויח shkoach everybody,
one פרק left to go.